<Story>
  <title>Thailand</title>
  <text clear="clear">This document is made from the Thailand article on Wikipedia for demonstration purpose.</text>
  <photo clear="clear" position="right">
    <source Source="http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/b/b8/Thailand_map_CIA.png"/>
    <caption>Map of Thailand</caption>
  </photo>
  <text clear="clear">Thailand (pronounced /ˈtaɪlænd/ TYE-land  or /ˈtaɪlənd/[5]; Thai: ราชอาณาจักรไทย Ratcha Anachak Thai, IPA: [râːtɕʰa ʔaːnaːtɕɑ̀k tʰɑj]( listen)) is an independent country that lies in the heart of Southeast Asia. It is bordered to the north by Burma and Laos, to the east by Laos and Cambodia, to the south by the Gulf of Thailand and Malaysia, and to the west by the Andaman Sea and the southern extremity of Burma. Its maritime boundaries include Vietnam  in the Gulf of Thailand to the southeast and Indonesia  and India  in the Andaman Sea to the southwest.</text>
  <photo clear="clear" position="left">
    <source Source="http://internationalagprograms2.dasnr.okstate.edu/internationalstudents/International%20Student%20Individual%20Pages/Paula%20Smithheisler/Thai_temple.jpg"/>
    <caption>Golden Buddha symbols of Thailand</caption>
  </photo>
  <text clear="clear">The country is a kingdom, a constitutional monarchy with King Bhumibol Adulyadej, the ninth king of the House of Chakri, who has reigned since 1946, making him the world's longest-serving current head of state and the longest-reigning  monarch in Thai history.  The king is officially titled as the Head of State, the Head of the Armed Forces, an Upholder of the Buddhist religion, and the Defender of all Faiths. The largest city in Thailand is Bangkok, the capital, which is also the country's center of political, commercial, industrial and cultural activities.</text>
  <text clear="clear">Thailand is the world's 50th largest country in terms of total area (slightly smaller than Yemen and slightly larger than Spain), with a surface area of approximately 513,000 km2 (198,000 sq mi), and the 21st most-populous country, with approximately 64 million people. About 75% of the population is ethnically Thai, 14% is of Chinese  origin, and 3% is ethnically Malay; the rest belong to minority groups including Mons, Khmers and various hill tribes. There are approximately 2.2 million legal and illegal migrants in Thailand. Thailand has also attracted a number of expatriates  from developed countries.  The country's official language is Thai.</text>
  <text clear="clear">Thailand has a prevalence of Buddhism that ranks among the highest in the world. The national religion is Theravada  Buddhism which is practiced by more than 94.7% of all Thais. Muslims make up 4.6% of the population and 0.7% belong to other religions.  Thai culture and traditions are mainly influenced by Chinese, and to a lesser degree, by Indian culture, along with Burma, Laos and Cambodia. Thailand experienced rapid economic growth between 1985 and 1995 and is a newly industrialized country with tourism, due to well-known tourist destinations such as Pattaya, Bangkok, and Phuket, and exports contributing significantly to the economy.</text>
  <header clear="clear">
    <header> History</header>
  </header>
  <photo clear="clear" position="left">
    <source Source="http://blogs.statravel.com/journal/region_images/asia_thailand_bangkok_wat.jpg"/>
    <caption>Wat Po</caption>
  </photo>
  <text clear="clear">The region known as Thailand has been inhabited by humans since the Paleolithic  period, about 10,000 years ago. Similar to other regions in Southeast Asia, it was heavily influenced by the culture and religions of India, starting with the kingdom of Funan around the 1st century CE.</text>
  <text clear="clear">After the fall of the Khmer Empire in the 13th century, various states thrived there, such as the various Tai, Mon, Khmer and Malay kingdoms, as seen through the numerous archaeological sites and artifacts that are scattered throughout the Siamese landscape. Prior to the 12th century however, the first Thai or Siamese state is traditionally considered to be the Buddhist kingdom of Sukhothai, which was founded in 1238.</text>
  <text clear="clear">Following the decline and fall of the Khmer empire in the 13th–14th century, the Buddhist Tai kingdoms of Sukhothai, Lanna and Lan Chang were on the ascension. However, a century later, the power of Sukhothai was overshadowed by the new kingdom of Ayutthaya, established in the mid-14th century in the lower Chao Phraya River or Menam area.</text>
  <text clear="clear">Ayutthaya's expansion centered along the Menam while in the northern valley the Lanna Kingdom and other small Tai city-states ruled the area. Thailand retained a tradition of trade with its neighbouring states, from China  to India, Persia and Arab lands. Ayutthaya became one of the most vibrant trading centres in Asia. European traders arrived in the 16th century, beginning with the Portuguese, followed by the French, Dutch  and English.</text>
  <photo clear="clear" position="right">
    <source Source="http://www.chantrathai.com/talatthai/wp-content/uploads/2009/05/picture1.jpg"/>
    <caption>Smile is part of the Culture</caption>
  </photo>
  <header clear="clear">
    <header> Demographics</header>
  </header>
  <text clear="clear">The official language of Thailand is Thai, a Kradai language closely related to Lao, Shan in Burma, and numerous smaller languages spoken in an arc from Hainan  and Yunnan  south to the Malaysian border. It is the principal language of education and government and spoken throughout the country. The standard is based on the dialect of the central Thai people, and it is written in the Thai alphabet, an abugida script that evolved from the Khmer script. Several other dialects exist, and coincide with the regional designations. Southern Thai is spoken in the southern provinces, and Northern Thai is spoken in the provinces that were formally part of the independent kingdom of Lannathai.</text>
  <text clear="clear">Thailand is also host to several other minority languages, the largest of which is the Lao dialect of Isan  spoken in the northeastern provinces. Although sometimes considered a Thai dialect, it is a Lao dialect, and the region in where it is traditionally spoken was historically part of the Lao kingdom of Lan Xang. In the far south, Yawi, a dialect of Malay, is the primary language of the Malay Muslims. Chinese dialects are also spoken by the large Chinese population, Teochew being the dialect best represented.</text>
  <text clear="clear">Taboos in Thailand include touching someone's head or pointing with the feet, as the head is considered the most sacred and the foot the dirtiest part of the body.Thai society has been influenced in recent years by its widely available multi-language press and media. There are some English and numerous Thai and Chinese newspapers in circulation; most Thai popular magazines use English headlines as a chic glamor factor. Many large businesses in Bangkok operate in English as well as other languages.</text>
  <header clear="both">
    <header>Food and Hospitality</header>
  </header>
  <photo clear="clear" position="left">
    <source Source="http://www.thaitable.com/images/ingredients/pictures/5Thai%20mackerel.jpg"/>
    <caption>Delicious Fish</caption>
  </photo>
  <text clear="clear">Thai cuisine blends five fundamental tastes: sweet, spicy, sour, bitter and salty. Some common ingredients used in Thai cuisine include garlic, chillies, lime juice, lemon grass, and fish sauce. The staple food in Thailand is rice, particularly jasmine variety rice (also known as Hom Mali rice) which is included in almost every meal. Thailand is the world's largest exporter of rice, and Thais domestically consume over 100 kg of milled rice per person per year. Over 5000 varieties of rice from Thailand are preserved in the rice gene bank of the International Rice Research Institute (IRRI), based in the Philippines. The king of Thailand is the official patron of IRRI.</text>
  <text clear="none">Like most Asian cultures, respect towards ancestors is an essential part of Thai spiritual practice. Thais have a strong sense of hospitality and generosity, but also a strong sense of social hierarchy. Seniority is an important concept in Thai culture. Elders have by tradition ruled in family decisions or ceremonies. Older siblings have duties to younger ones.</text>
</Story>
